｢The once was a hungry crow｣
♪ ｢お 腹 空 かせた ｶﾗｽがいた｣
｢Who wanted to get some feed｣
♪ ｢なんとか 餌 に ありつきたい｣
｢If only this beak were longer｣
♪ ｢この くちばしが もっと長ければ｣
｢That feed would be a bit closer｣
♪ ｢あの餌が もっと こっちに来れば｣
♪ ～
♪ ～
｢A crow can think｣
｢ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える｣
｢can think... can think｣
♪ ｢考える 考える｣
Observe, propose a hypothesis, experiment and then consider results.
( 斎藤 )観察し 仮 説を立て 実験をし 考察する｡
Learn the way of scientific thought.
科学の考え方を学べ｡
We begin with a ｢Thinking Observation｣
(山本)まずは ｢考える観察｣から｡
An ant walking atop a notepad.
ﾉｰﾄの上を アリが歩いている｡
Let's try drawing a line across the ant's path.
アリの行く先に 線を引いてみる｡
It appears to dislike it but doesn't completely understand.
いやがったように見えたが よく わからない｡
Again we block its path with a line.
また 線で 道をふさぐ｡
It avoids the line.
線を よけた｡
This time we try to surround it with a circle.
今度は 丸で囲ってみる｡
Clearly it dislikes the line.
明らかに 線を いやがっている｡
It's cut off.
とじこめられた｡
It gets out, and we surround it one more time.
外に出して もう一度 囲ってみる｡
As we expect it's isolated.
やはり とじこめられた｡
Observe for a short while.
しばらく 観察する｡
It got out. Is it already used to them?
外に出てきた｡ もう 慣 れたのか？
It walks across the lines in equanimity.
線の上を 平気で歩いている｡
Let's try surrounding it with a new circle.
新しく 丸で囲ってみる｡
Once again, it has become unable to get out.
また 出られなくなった｡
It appears it hasn't gotten used to it.
慣れたわけでは ないようだ｡
What's going on here?
どういう事か｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
Today our problem deals with a magnet and some iron balls.
今日は 磁石 と鉄の玉を使った 問題です｡
This is a magnet.
これは 磁石です｡
If I bring it near the iron balls...
鉄の玉に近づけると… →
they stick together.
くっつきます｡
But the iron balls themselves...
でも 鉄の玉同士は…｡
of course don't stick together.
もちろん くっつきません｡
Okay so far?
ここまでは いいですか？
Next we affix the magnet to the desk with some tape.
では 磁石に ﾃｰﾌﾟをつけて つくえの上に固定します｡
Then we place another magnet of the same type atop it.
そして もう１まい 同じ磁石を 上にのせます｡
If we bring an iron ball close, it sticks.
そこに 鉄の玉を １つ近づけて くっつけます｡
Furthermore, we place one more iron ball atop...
更に もう一つ 鉄の玉を のっけると…｡
and this also sticks.
これも くっつきます｡
Now, this is the problem.
さて ここからが 問題です｡
What will happen if we raise the topmost iron ball?
上にある鉄の玉を持ち上げると 一体 どうなるでしょうか？
1. Only the ball we're holding will be raised.
１｡ 持っている鉄の玉だけが 上がる｡
2. The iron ball beneath will also be raised.
２｡ その下にある鉄の玉も いっしょに上がる｡
3. Furthermore, the magnet beneath will also be raised.
３｡ 更に その下にある磁石も
Well then, what will happen? We'll present the answer at the end of the program.
さてさて どうなるか｡ 答えは 番組の最後で発表します｡
Everyone, think really hard about this, won't you?
みなさん よ～く考えておいてくださいね｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
Now, the answer from earlier.
では 先ほどの答えです｡
Everyone, did you think carefully?
みなさん ちゃんと考えましたか？
Now, let's do it for real.
では 実さいに やってみましょう｡
Let's go.
いきますよ？
The answer it number 1.
答えは ２番でした｡
The two iron balls together are raised.
鉄の玉が ２つとも いっしょに持ち上がりました｡
Further more, if we try to raise the iron balls a bit further.
更に 玉を もう少し 持ち上げてみると… →
What do you suppose will happen?
どうなるでしょう？
I was surprised...
びっくりした…｡
it fell. Let's try that once more.
落ちてしまいました｡ もう一度 やってみましょう｡
As we saw, it falls. Why do you think that is?
やっぱり 落ちてしまいました｡ どうしてでしょう？
When iron is brought near a magnet, instantly...
鉄は 磁石に近づくと 一時的に 磁石…｡
From here on we think for ourselves.
ここから先は 自分で考えよう｡
From here everyone is a thinking crow.
これからは みんなが ｢考えるｶﾗｽ｣｡